Finding Aid for Philip E. Converse (1928-) Papers 1948-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip E. Converse papers 1948-1989
Converse, Philip E., 1928-
11.5 linear feet
Social psychologist and political scientist, professor of sociology and political science at the University of Michigan, and director of the University's Institute for Social Research. Series include biography; writings and lectures; correspondence; teaching materials; study materials; conferences, professional associations and committees; administrative files; grant proposals; and photographs.
90137 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Philip E. Converse (donor no. 7677 ) in August 1989.
The collection is open to research, except for closed files in Box 12.
Philip Ernest Converse was born in Concord, New Hampshire, on November 17, 1928. He attended Denison University in Granville, Ohio, where he earned a B.A. in English in 1949. The following year he received a master's degree in English literature from the State University of Iowa. Six years later, after a period of study in France, he enrolled at the University of Michigan in 1956 to pursue his interest in the social sciences, and earned a M.A. in sociology in 1956, followed by a Ph.D. in social psychology in 1958. In 1951, he married Jean G. McDonnell, a social scientist expert in interviewing techniques.
Converse joined the University of Michigan faculty as an assistant professor of sociology in 1960, was appointed associate professor of political science in 1963, and associate professor of sociology in 1964. Quick to establish a reputation as an outstanding social psychologist and empirical political scientist, he was appointed professor of sociology and political science in 1965. He was named the Robert C. Angell Professor of Political Science and Sociology in 1975, and Robert Cooley Angell Distinguished University Professor of Political Science and Sociology in 1982. He was selected as the 1987 Henry Russel Lecturer, the University's highest honor given to a senior faculty member. The University of Michigan Research Club, when nominating Converse for the award, summarized his contributions by noting, "Professor Converse made many contributions to the development of the Michigan Program, which 25 years ago revolutionized political science research. The great innovation of this program was its heavy emphasis on quantitative methods applied to empirical research, in general, and to survey research, in particular. It was unique at that time, but subsequently became the model copied in numerous other departments in this country and in Europe. This 'movement' brought political science into much closer intellectual contact with sociology, social psychology and economics."
Converse is also well known for his work with the University of Michigan Institute for Social Research (ISR). Converse began his affiliation with the institute as assistant study director of the Survey Research Center in 1956, and by 1986 had been appointed director of the institute. While en route to the directorship he headed several of the institute's important components. In 1962 he was named associate director of the Inter-university Consortium for Political Research, a partnership between the Survey Research Center at the University of Michigan and several other universities in the United States. He was named program director of the Survey Research Center in 1965, and director of the Center for Political Studies in 1982. When he assumed his duties as institute director, he did so at a crucial time when federal funds for social research were being slashed. The institute relies almost entirely on non-university grants and contracts to carry on its work, and he was instrumental in securing a number of new funding sources. He also strengthened the ties between the institute and the university by drawing on the research skills of university professors from various departments and schools.
Converse is the author of numerous books and articles on a wide range of political and sociological topics. Many of his works are considered standards in their fields. His book The American Voter (coauthored with Angus Campbell, Warren E. Miller and Donald E. Stokes) is considered a classic. It pioneered the use of new methods to describe voting behavior in the United States. Vietnam and the Silent Majority (coauthored with Milton Rosenberg and Sidney Verba) and The Human Meaning of Social Change (with Angus Campbell) were innovative works in group political behavior. The Quality of American Life (coauthored with Angus Campbell) studied Americans' sense of well-being. His work not only encompasses the United States but other nations as well, such as his award-winning Political Representation in France (coauthored with Roy Pierce). His articles have appeared in a variety of well-known scholarly books and journals. Among his most influential articles are, "The Nature of Belief Systems in Mass Publics," which has had enormous influence on research in the field of political ideology, and "Of Time and Partisan Stability," which demonstrated the linkage between family socialization and individual partisan identification.
In addition to his research contributions, Converse has made distinguished contributions as a statesman of the social sciences. He has served on numerous committees of the many professional, public service, and honorary organizations in which he is active. These include The American Political Science Association, The American Sociological Association, The Social Science Research Council, and The National Research Council. He was president of the American Political Science Association in 1983-84 and of the International Society of Political Psychology in 1980-81.
Converse has received many awards during his career. He has received honorary doctorate degrees from Denison University and the University of Chicago, and has been awarded numerous fellowships, including the Fulbright, Guggenheim, and Russell Sage. He is an elected member of such notable societies as the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, The American Philosophical Society, and the National Academy of Science.
Converse left the University of Michigan in 1989 to become director of the Center for Advanced Study in Behavioral Sciences in Stanford, California. He was chosen from a field of some 150 candidates in a nationwide search for a new director. The independent research center is near the campus of Stanford University, and is considered one of the nation's most prestigious "think tanks."
The Philip Converse collection is divided into ten series: Biography; Writings and Lectures; Correspondence; Teaching Materials; Study Materials; Conferences, Professional Associations and Committees; Administrative Files; Grant Proposals; Photographs; and Closed Files. These divisions are designed to provide an overview of Philip Converse's career at the University of Michigan and document its three main components: scholar, professor, and administrator.
Subjects:
Social psychology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biography
  - Biographical material (includes vitae) (Box 1)
    Biography (8 folders) consists of background material on Converse, including vitae, bibliographies, completed questionnaires, congratulatory letters, outside employment offers, book reviews, and newspaper articles. Materials relating to his applications for various fellowships are contained in this series and include brief autobiographical career accounts. In 1987, Converse's wife, Jean, authored Survey Research in the United States: Roots and Emergence, 1890-1960. Two chapters from her book which detail the origins of the University of Michigan Institute for Social Research, are included in this series. The biographical materials are, on the whole, particularly helpful in reconstructing the various stages of Converse's career and outlining his major research accomplishments.
  - Book Reviews (Box 1)
  - Fellowship material (includes applications, career accounts, and correspondence), 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Job offers, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "The Survey Research Center at Michigan: From the Margins of Government" and "The Academic Establishment of Survey Research: A Summary and Evaluation" (Chapters from Survey Research in the United States: Roots and Emergence 1890-1960, 1987 by Jean Converse) (Box 1)
- Writings and Lectures
  Writings and Lectures (1.5 linear feet) consists of articles and book chapters, as well as lectures delivered to various groups and associations around the world. They are arranged chronologically, and date from the time Converse began his graduate studies at the University of Michigan to the time of his departure from Ann Arbor for the Center for Advanced Study of the Behavioral Sciences. To distinguish his speaking career from his writing career, lectures and paper presentations are grouped separately. For a complete listing of Converse`s writings and major speeches see his vitae and bibliographies in the Biography series.
  - Writings
    - 1956
      - "Political Party Identification in the State of Michigan" (Box 1)
      - Reviews (1956-1979) (Box 1)
    - 1957
      - "The American Voter" 1957-1959, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - "Group Influence in Voting Behavior" (dissertation proposal) (Box 1)
      - "The Shifting Role of Class in Political Attitudes and Behavior" (Box 1)
      - Press Releases 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1960
      - 1960 Election (Box 1)
      - The Progressive (articles), 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962
      - "Eisenhower et de Gaulle: les generaux devant l'opinion" (co-authored with Georges Dupeux) (Box 1)
    - 1964
      - "Attitudes and Non-Attitudes" 1964-1968 (with correspondence) (Box 1)
      - "The Availability and Quality of Sample Survey Data in Archives Within the United States" (Box 1)
      - "The Behavioral Approach to Political Research" (Box 1)
      - "Models of Voting Change" (Box 1)
      - "The Nature of Belief Systems in Mass Publics" (Box 1)
      - "The Problem of Party Distances in Models of Voting Change" (Box 1)
      - 1964 Election (Box 1)
    - 1965
      - "Social Cleavages in the 1964 Election" (Box 1)
      - "Vote Report Validation" (Box 1)
      - "Who Votes and for Whom" (Box 1)
    - 1966
      - "Public Opinion and the War in Vietnam" (Box 1)
    - 1968
      - "Of Time and Partisan Stability" (Box 1)
      - "Time Budgets" (Box 1)
        (for International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences)
    - 1969
      - "Parties and Issues in the 1968 Election" (Box 1)
      - "Time Budget" (Box 1)
    - 1970
      - "Who Voted for Whom in 1968" (Box 1)
    - 1971
      - "The Mail Survey of Women Oriented to the Political Science Profession" (co-authored by Jean Converse) (Box 1)
    - 1972
      - "Changes in the American Electorate" (Box 1)
      - "Measures of Perceived Overall Quality of Life" (Box 1)
      - "Of Time and Partisan Stability" (Box 1)
      - "Perceived Party Distances in Norwegian Voting" (coauthored by Henry Valen) (Box 1)
      - "Preface to Methodological Volume" (Box 1)
    - 1973
      - "Non-Attitudes and American Public Opinion: The Examination of A Thesis", Rejoinder to (Box 1)
    - 1975
      - International Political Science Association (IPSA) "Mass-Elite" (graphs) (Box 1)
      - "Measures of the Perceived Overall Quality of Life" (coauthored by Willard Rogers) (Box 1)
    - 1978
      - "A Dynamic Simultaneous Equation Model of Electoral Choice" (Box 1)
      - "Societal Growth and the Quality of Life" (Box 1)
      - "Toward More Cumulative Inquiry: The General Social Survey," (paper and background) (Box 1)
      - "What the Rocks are Like: The New CPS Election Study Panel", 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1980
      - Angus Campbell Memorial Statements 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - Comment on Judd and Milburn's "Belief System" (Box 1)
      - "Ideological Conceptualization and Party Identification, 1956-1976" (Box 1)
      - "Ideology and the Water's Edge" (Box 1)
      - "The Study of Voting" (1980-1982) (paper and background for National Research Council) (Box 1)
    - 1982
      - "Response to Lecture by Professor Cronbach" (Box 2)
      - "The Impact of Polls on National Leadership" (Box 2)
    - 1983
      - National Institute on Aging (report drafts) (Box 2)
      - "Outward Bound," (manuscript for Henry Valen's birthday) (Box 2)
    - 1985
      - "Power and the Monopoly of Information" (Box 2)
      - University of Chicago (manuscript) (Box 2)
    - 1987
      - "Changing Conceptions of Public Opinion in the Political Process" (Box 2)
    - Undated
      - "Salt Passage" (satirical essay) (Box 2)
  - Lectures
    - 1958
      - "Status Polarization and Social Structure" (American Sociology Society meeting) (Box 2)
    - 1962
      - La Napoule Conference (paper and related correspondence) (Box 2)
    - 1963
      - "A Network of Topical Data Archives in the U.S." (conference paper) (Box 2)
    - 1964
      - American Sociological Association Meeting (Box 2)
      - Mass Ideology (Box 2)
    - 1966
      - "Survey Research and the Decoding of Patterns in Ecological Data" (conference paper) (Box 2)
    - 1967
      - Information Explosion circa 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1970
      - "Basic Cleavages in French Politics and the Disorders of May and June, 1968" (conference paper coauthored with Roy Pierce) (Box 2)
    - 1972
      - "Stability and Change in Sources of French Electoral Behavior" (conference paper) (Box 2)
    - 1980
      - University of Chicago Address for Honorary Degree (Box 2)
    - 1981
      - Information and Remarks, Association of Graduate Schools Conference (Box 2)
      - Economic Dinner Group (Box 2)
      - Mannheim Address (Box 2)
      - "Measuring the Quality of Life" (Angelo Rizzoli Foundation Paper) (Box 2)
      - Statements Before the National Science Board (Box 2)
      - Quality of Life (miscellaneous speeches) circa 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982
      - Congressional Testimony (Box 2)
    - 1983
      - "Generalization and the Social Psychology of `Other Worlds'," Katz-Newcomb Lecture (Box 2)
    - 1984
      - Power and Information Speech (Box 2)
    - 1986
      - "The Enduring Impact of the Vietnam War on American Public Opinion" (conference paper) (Box 2)
    - 1987
      - "Perspectives on the Democratic Process," Henry Russel Lecture (Box 2)
    - 1988
      - Rackham 50th Anniversary Presentation (untitled remarks) (Box 2)
    - Undated
      - General Lecture on Survey Research Center (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (4.5 linear feet) is the largest of the series, and is divided into three sub-series: Chronological, Organizations, and Electronic Mail. Chronological consists of both incoming and outgoing correspondence and is arranged by year. Correspondents include scientists in Converse's field, as well as miscellaneous groups and organizations. The Organizations sub-series is comprised of incoming and outgoing correspondence which Converse conducted on a large scale with organizations with which he was affiliated. The sub-series is arranged alphabetically by organization name. The majority of it concerns the International Society of Political Psychology, which Converse has been affiliated with since its inception. The third sub-series consists of paper copies of incoming and outgoing University of Michigan electronic mail messages from 1987-1989, when Converse was director of the Institute for Social Research. It is chronologically arranged.
  - Chronological
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1962, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1963, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1964, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1965, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1970, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1971, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 1972, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1973, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1975, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1977 (Box 4)
    - 1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1979, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1981 (Box 4)
    - 1982 (Box 4)
    - 1983 (Box 4)
    - 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1986 (Box 5)
    - 1987 (Box 5)
    - 1988 (Box 5)
    - 1989 (Box 5)
  - Organizations
    - American Political Science Association 1982-1985, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - International Society of Political Psychology 1979-1987, 13 folders (Box 5)
    - Russell Sage Foundation 1981-1988 (Box 5)
    - Social Science Research Council 1975-1989 (Box 5)
  - Electronic Mail
    - 1987 (Box 5)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
- Teaching Materials
  Teaching Materials (0.5 linear feet) includes syllabi, examinations, lecture notes, and teaching evaluations from Converse's tenure in both the political science and sociology departments. The series is arranged by topic and mostly documents the years 1960-1986. Lecture notes are sporadic and exist primarily from the early 1960s. Examinations are comprised of copies of midterm, final, and doctoral examinations administered by Converse from 1965 to 1985. Teaching evaluations include computerized questionnaire forms and tally sheets, and remarks written by students regarding the quality of Converse's teaching. Evaluations exist for the years 1972 to 1983.
  - General 1960-1988, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Course Evaluations 1972-1986 (Box 6)
  - Course Outlines 1958 (Box 6)
  - Lecture Notes, Outlines 1961-1962 (Box 6)
- Study Materials
  Study Materials (2 linear feet) are divided into two sub-series: Domestic Studies and International Studies. The division represents the different scopes of Converse's studies. The files are arranged chronologically and include instruction booklets, questionnaires, and project codes used in computing and tallying responses. Background material and relevant correspondence is filed with the study to which it pertains. (The researcher should note that the series Grant Proposals also includes materials on studies which received funding). Domestic Studies include those related to elections, time budgeting, and quality of life, and date from 1958 to 1986, although materials from as far back as 1948 are also present. The Quality of Life study is the most thoroughly documented. International Studies include political studies conducted in France, in other European countries, and in Latin America. In several of these international studies, Converse served as the project coordinator, overseeing the field work of others. Correspondence with the field workers comprise a large portion of the materials, particularly those from the French studies (most of the correspondence is in French).
  - Domestic Studies
    - 1948-1959
      - Project Codes (Box 6)
    - 1954
      - Project #623 (instruction booklet) (Box 6)
    - 1956
      - Project #417-Election Study
        - Questionnaires (Box 6)
        - Budget (Box 6)
      - Project #651 (instruction booklet) (Box 6)
      - Project #646 (interim election study codes) (Box 6)
    - 1958
      - Project #431-1958 Election Study (Box 6)
    - 1961
      - Project #440-Panel Mortality (Box 6)
    - 1963
      - Pre-Election Graphs (Box 6)
    - 1964
      - Projects #473-Post Election Study (Box 6)
    - 1965
      - Time Use Study (with updates, 1974) (Box 6)
    - 1966
      - Project #504-Election Study Questionnaire (Box 6)
    - 1969
      - Time Budget Project
        - General (Box 6)
        - Tables (Box 6)
      - "Quality of Life" 1969-1974 (general), 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1971 (Box 7)
      - Election Time Series Analysis (Box 7)
      - "Quality of Life"
        - Instruction booklet (Box 7)
        - Pretests (Box 7)
    - 1972
      - Election Time Series Analysis (Box 7)
    - 1973
      - Political Socialization Study (instruction book) (Box 7)
    - 1977
      - "Quality of Life" (instruction booklet) (Box 7)
    - 1978
      - 1978 Congressional Campaign Study (instruction book) (Box 7)
      - Health in Detroit (instruction book) (Box 7)
      - "Quality of Life"
        - Interview Schedules (Box 7)
        - Questionnaire (Box 7)
    - 1985
      - "The Intersection of Personal and National History"
        - General (1983-1985) (Box 7)
        - Questionnaires (Box 7)
        - Questionnaires and Responses, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - "Quality of Life" (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
      - "Survey of Consumer Attitudes" (questionnaire) (Box 7)
    - 1986
      - "Quality of Employment Survey" (Social Science Research Council), 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1958
      - French Study Project #440 (Box 7)
      - French Study Notebooks (Box 7)
    - 1960-1969
      - French Study [note: largely in French]
        - General (includes correspondence), 3 folders (Box 7)
        - Georges Dupeux Articles (Box 7)
        - Reference Questionnaires (Box 7)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 8)
      - "Five Nation Study" [Finland, Japan, Norway, Spain, Sweden] (Box 8)
    - 1965-1969
      - Canadian Study
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Questionnaires (Box 8)
    - 1968-1973
      - Latin American Study
        - Ford Foundation (Box 8)
        - Brazilian Study (Box 8)
        - Peter McDonough Brazilian Study (largely correspondence) (Box 8)
- Conferences, Professional Associations and Committees
  The series Conferences, Professional Associations and Committees (1.5 linear feet) documents Converse's active professional life for the years 1962-1989. Files in the sub-series Conferences contain materials from conferences in which Converse participated. They are arranged chronologically, and include conference bulletins, proceedings and correspondence which document his contributions. Files on the professional associations to which Converse belonged and professional committees on which he served are arranged alphabetically by organization name in a separate sub-series, and include correspondence, reports, and proceedings.
  - Conferences
    - 1962
      - Bergen Conference (Box 8)
      - Southern Conference (Box 8)
    - 1964
      - American Association for Public Opinion Research Conference (Box 8)
      - American History Association Conference (Box 8)
      - Cologne Conference (Box 8)
      - Political Issues and Business Conference (Box 8)
    - 1966
      - International Social Science Council Conference, Evian, France (Box 8)
    - 1967
      - Wayne State Symposium (Box 8)
    - 1970
      - World Congress of Sociology, Varna (Box 8)
    - 1976
      - IPSA Conference, Edinburgh (Box 8)
    - 1979
      - Social Science Research Council Conferences (Box 8)
    - 1980
      - Meeting of Committee on A Study of Research-Doctorate Programs in the United States (Box 8)
    - 1981
      - ISPP Mannheim Conference (Box 8)
    - 1982
      - Angelo Rizzoli Foundation Meeting, Venice (Box 8)
    - 1983
      - Advanced Research Seminar on Cognitive Aspects of Survey Methodology, 2 volumes (Box 8)
    - 1985
      - Academica Sinica Conference (Box 8)
      - Presidency Conference, Gerald Ford Presidential Library (Box 8)
      - Queen's College Conference (Box 8)
    - 1987
      - Bureau of the Census Annual Research Conference (Box 8)
      - University of Essex Visit and Lecture (Box 8)
  - Professional Associations and Committees (Box 9)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences 1983-1989, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science 1982-1988 (Box 9)
    - American Bar Association 1985-1988 (Box 9)
    - American Political Science Association Committee on the Status of Women in the Profession 1970-1971 (Box 9)